{"tossups": [{"question": "Court painter Daniel Maclise depicted this monarch meeting a noblewoman <em>At</em> <em>Hampton Court</em> in one painting. This monarch appears on the bottom left approaching the royal party of Francis I in the landscape painting <em>Field of the Cloth of Gold</em>. This man employed foreigner Hans Holbein the Younger, who depicted this king in a portrait situated next to one of Jane Seymour and this man's father Henry VII [[the Seventh]]. For ten points, name this English king who is depicted in several portraits with his six wives.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry VIII</u></b> [[the Eighth]]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Secretary of War Jefferson Davis sent this man to Europe to study the tactics of the Crimean War, and later in his life, he would serve as governor of New Jersey. In letters to his wife, this general describes himself as \"the power of the land\" and the commander in chief as a \"well meaning baboon.\" This general was removed from command following the Battle of Antietam, and would challenge President Lincoln in the Election of 1864. For ten points, name this prideful Union general, known for his cautiousness in battle.", "answer": "George B. <b><u>McClellan</u></b> (prompt on \"Little Mac\" or \"Young Napoleon\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A member of this family wrote the book <em>On the Art of the Cinema</em> and ordered the kidnapping of film director Shin Sang-ok. Members of this family promote the ideology of \"military first\" or \"Songun\" and a quasi-religion called \"Juche\" [[JOO-cheh]]. A member of this family met with Dennis Rodman in 2013 and was rumored to be transferring power to his sister Yo-jong due to health issues in 2020. Dictators Il-sung, Jong-il, and Jong-un belong to, for ten points, what family that controls North Korea?", "answer": "<b><u>Kim</u></b> family (accept <b><u>Kim</u></b> Il-sung; <b><u>Kim</u></b> Jong-il; or <b><u>Kim</u></b> Jong-un)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In a failed attempt to prevent this event, a route along Appel Quay was decided upon by Oskar Potiorek. A false turn by Leopold Lojka [[LOY-kuh]] resulted in this event, which was preceded by a failed attack with a hand grenade. An FN Model 1910 was used to carry out this attack, which also resulted in the death of its central target\u2019s wife, Sophie. The Black Hand helped organize this event, which was perpetrated by the Bosnian Serb Gavrilo Princip.  For ten points, name this 1914 attack that killed the heir presumptive of Austria-Hungary.", "answer": "<b><u>Assassination</u></b> of Archduke <b><u>Franz Ferdinand</u></b> (accept clear-knowledge equivalents for \"assassination\"; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the 1970s, this man was nominated for Best Recording for Children at the Grammys for an educational album featuring [this man] <em>and His Gang vs. Mr. Tooth Decay</em>. Jimmy Carter tasked this athlete with a 1980 tour of Africa to endorse the boycott of the Moscow Olympics. In an effort to legitimize his regime, dictator Mobutu Sese Seko hosted a contest between this athlete and George Foreman, the so-called \"Rumble in the Jungle.\" Cassius Clay was once the name of, for ten points, which boxer, known as \"The Greatest\"?", "answer": "Muhammad <b><u>Ali</u></b> (accept Cassius Marcellus <b><u>Clay</u></b> Jr. before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Moro of Mindanao declared one of these specific conflicts after the government of Ferdinand Marcos killed many of its acolytes in the Corregidor massacre. During one of these specific conflicts, scholar Usman dan Fodio united many of the Hausa independent states after being appointed \"Commander of the Faithful.\" Ottoman sultan Mehmed V formally declared a \"Great\" one of these religious wars against the Allies during World War One. For ten points, name these Islamic holy wars, often considered a counterpart to a Christian \"Crusade.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Jihad</u></b> (prompt on answers involving \"Religious warfare\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Civil War general Benjamin Butler was given the nickname \u201cSpoons\u201d for taking silverware from a woman during the Union\u2019s occupation of this city, the most populous in the Confederacy. In another conflict, Edward Pakenham was defeated in this city by a force assisted by pirate Jean Lafitte [[lah-FEET]] in a battle fought after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent. Andrew Jackson won the Battle of, for ten points, what city major port city annexed into the Union by the Louisiana Purchase?", "answer": "<b><u>New Orleans</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Nouvelle-Orl\u00e9ans</u></b>; or <b><u>NOLA</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This prime minister ordered British forces to bombard Alexandria in response to the 'Urabi [[oo-RAH-bee]] revolt. The Hawarden [[HAR-den]] Kite was an infamous news scoop that suggested this man supported Irish Home Rule. This leader attacked a prominent political rival over their response to the \u201cBulgarian Horrors\u201d in his Midlothian campaign. For ten points, name this four-time Liberal British prime minister during the nineteenth century and rival of Benjamin Disraeli.", "answer": "William Ewart <b><u>Gladstone</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, one participant revoked their ambassador in Sweden for openly harboring deserters. Mark Satin wrote a \"Manual\" which taught men how to integrate into Canadian society during this war, and Arlo Guthrie recounts traveling to Whitehall Street in New York and intentionally acting mentally ill in the protest song \"Alice's Restaurant Massacree.\" Men like Bill Clinton and Dick Cheney faced accusations of dodging, for ten points, what 1960s and 1970s conflict in Southeast Asia?", "answer": "<b><u>Vietnam</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Second Indochina</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This figure incorporated a band he managed, Lou Reed's Velvet Underground, into his multimedia art show, the <em>Exploding Plastic Inevitable</em>. This man was shot after the author of the radical feminist work, the <em>SCUM Manifesto</em>, Valerie Solanas, claimed he had too much control over her life. Silkscreen ink was used by this artist to depict the preeminent Communist leader Mao Zedong. <em>32 Campbell's Soup Cans</em> and the <em>Marilyn Diptych</em> were created by, for ten points, which American Pop artist?", "answer": "Andy <b><u>Warhol</u></b> (or Andrew <b><u>Warhol</u></b>a, Jr.)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An impending munitions delivery from the SS <em>Ypiranga</em> [[ee-pee-RAHN-gah]] led to an attack in this city, which was then under a six-month occupation by one country following the <em>Tampico</em> Affair, which in turn led to the downfall of Victoriano Huerta. Half a century earlier, this city was the subject of the first amphibious assault in U.S. military history. Winfield Scott led an invasion of central Mexico through, for ten points, what Mexican port city?", "answer": "<b><u>Veracruz</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The explosion of a water tank in Mayak led to a nuclear disaster in the southern portion of this range, irradiating nearby Lake Karachay. A city nestled in this range named Magnitogorsk became an industrial hub in the 1930s due to a mountain there being made up of fifty-five percent iron ore. The Council for Evacuation, or GKO, moved over 1500 factories beyond this mountain range in the midst of Operation Barbarossa. For ten points, name this mountain range that historically divided the European and Asian portions of Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Ural</u></b> Mountains (or <b><u>Ural</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Ural</u></b>skiye gory)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This character is enticed by a sign to \"Join the Army and See the World\" and dies in the jungles of Vietnam in an underground protest film by Whitney Lee Savage. Margaret Thatcher labelled the European Parliament with this fictional character's name due to its perceived ineffectiveness. Despite making a short appearance in <em>Plane Crazy</em>, this character and his paramour first appeared in the short film <em>Steamboat Willie</em>. Walt Disney originally voiced, for ten points, which mascot of the Disney corporation?", "answer": "<b><u>Mickey</u></b> Mouse", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man commanded a fleet that seized a treasure worth over thirty million present-day pounds from the <em>S\u00e3o Filipe</em> [[SOW fil-EEP-ee]]. This man commanded a raid that tried to land at El Puntal [[EHL [[PUHN-tahl]] while destroying dozens of Spanish capital ships in the Bay of C\u00e1diz, known as the \"singeing [[SINJ-ing]] of the King of Spain's beard.\" Earlier, this man commanded the flagship <em>Golden Hind</em> and claimed \"New Albion\" in California. For ten points, name this British privateer who led a 1577 to 1580 circumnavigation of the world.", "answer": "Francis <b><u>Drake</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this modern-day country, a breakaway general who was fond of using a metaphor about plucking the tail off a horse held off Metellus Pius and Pompey for seven years. This present-day country was the location of Quintus Sertorius's attempt to rebel against Rome. Hannibal's attack on Saguntum in this present-day country began the Second Punic War. Hadrian and Trajan were both born in what is now this country. For ten points, name this country where Romans expanded cities such as Valentia, Corduba, and Toletum, or modern Toledo.", "answer": "<b><u>Spain</u></b> (accept Kingdom of <b><u>Spain</u></b>; or Reino de <b><u>Espana</u></b>; accept Roman <b><u>Hispania</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Despite playing for the Browns, Joe Gedeon earned a lifetime ban for knowledge of this event. Former federal judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis ignored an acquittal of eight men during a faulty trial concerning this event and banned the defendants from one sport. Despite having a .375 batting average and committing zero errors, \"Shoeless Joe\" Jackson was banned for his alleged involvement in this event. Owner Charles Comiskey's poor wages led to, for ten points, which baseball scandal where a team threw the 1919 World Series in exchange for money?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Sox</u></b> Scandal (accept descriptions which include the <b><u>White Sox</u></b> throwing the <b><u>World Series</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A school of historiographical thought named for Columbia professor William Archibald Dunning was accused of taking \"white supremacist\" stances on this time period, leading to a direct refutation by W.E.B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYSS]] in his book <em>Black</em> [this era]. In one thesis, historian Erich Foner disputes that \"carpetbaggers\" and \"scalawags\" were the cause of the failure of this period. The military occupation of the rebelling Confederate States occurred during, for ten points, which period in the South in the 19th century?", "answer": "<b><u>Reconstruction</u></b> (accept <em>Black</em> <em><b><u>Reconstruction</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man helped organize Illinois\u2019 Populist Party and ran for U.S. Congress in</u></b> <b><u>1895, losing to Hugh R. Belknap. After being charged for bribery, this man switched</u></b> <b><u>careers from being a civil lawyer to a criminal defense (+)</u> attorney. This man presided over a case where eleven Black men, including Ossian Sweet, killed a white man, as well as a case that the </b><em><b>Chicago Tribune</b></em><b> dubbed \u201cThe Trial (*) </b>of the Century.\u201d For ten points, name this prominent criminal defense attorney who defended Leopold and Loeb [[LOBE]], as well as John Scopes, in the \"Monkey Trial.\"", "answer": "Clarence <b><u>Darrow</u></b> (or Clarence Seward <b><u>Darrow</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The poet of</u> </b><em><b><u>Morgante</u></b></em><b><u>, Luigi Pulci [[PUHL-chi]], wrote a verse poem celebrating</u></b> <b><u>this nobleman's victory in a 1469 jousting tournament. To acquire the support of this</u></b> <b><u>man, Sultan Qaitbay presented him with a (+)</u> giraffe which this man let roam the city streets, according to poet Antonio Costanzo. This politician survived an assassination attempt during the Pazzi Conspiracy, an act sanctioned by the sitting Pope and rival of his family (*) </b>Sixtus IV. For ten points, name this \"Magnificent\" ruler of Florence, the grandson of Cosimo.", "answer": "<b><u>Lorenzo</u></b> de' <b><u>Medici</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; accept <b><u>Lorenzo</u></b> di Piero de' <b><u>Medici</u></b>; accept <b><u>Lorenzo the Magnificent</u></b> or <b><u>Lorenzo di Magnifico</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Lorenzo the Magnificent\" or \"Lorenzo di Magnifico\" after mention)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A passage in Pliny says that an important statue of this god had wool binding</u></b> <b><u>around the feet and was hollowed out and filled with oil that was removed only once</u></b> <b><u>per year. A fresco discovered at Pompeii shows this god wearing a white veil and</u></b> <b><u>carrying a (+)</u> sickle. This god, whom the Romans believes patronized an archaic Golden Age in Italy, was the namesake of a winter (*) </b>festival during which masters waited on slaves. For ten points, identify this father of Jupiter who the Romans worshipped at a cult center on the Capitoline hill.", "answer": "<b><u>Saturn</u></b> (accept <b><u>Saturn</u></b>alia; do not accept \"Cronus\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>A person in this occupation nicknamed \"Madre Conchita\" likely masterminded</u></b> <b><u>the assassination of former president, Alvaro Obregon [[oh-breh-GOHN]] at Bombilla</u></b> <b><u>[[bohm-BEE-yah]] Cafe by Jos\u00e9 de Le\u00f3n Toral. The constructed language</u> </b><em><b><u>lingua ignota</u> </b></em><b><u>was created by Hildegard (+)</u> von Bingen, who held this occupation in the County Palatine. Martin Luther first housed and later married a noble named (*) </b>Katharina who once was in this occupation. For ten points, name this monastic profession in the Catholic church held exclusively by women.", "answer": "<b><u>Nun</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Abbess</u></b>; or <b><u>Sister</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A Venetian convert led a subset of these states and built his namesake mosque</u></b> <b><u>to impress Lalla Lalla Oum, a princess of the Kabyle [[KAH-beel]]. Ships of this polity</u></b> <b><u>departing from Sale [[SAH-leh]] (+)</u> traveled across the Atlantic during a 17th century raid on Iceland in search of slaves. With assistance from Sweden and Sicily, the U.S. fought two namesake (*) </b>wars with people of these states, culminating in a blockade of Tripoli. For ten points, name these historical \u201cpirate states\u201d of the North African coast.", "answer": "<b><u>Barbary</u></b> States (accept <b><u>Barbary</u></b> Coast; or <b><u>Berber</u></b> Coast; prompt on \"North Africa\"; prompt on more specific answers such as \"Algeria,\" \"Tripolitania,\" and \"Tunisia\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2017, this state's officials brought in Irula tribesmen from the Indian</u></b> <b><u>subcontinent to capture invasive Burmese Pythons. Since the 1990s, a landfill in the</u></b> <b><u>south of this state has been piled over with soil to avoid odors, leading to the</u></b> <b><u>affectionate nickname \"Mount Trashmore.\" Lake (+)</u> Hell 'n Blazes is the source of this state's St. Johns River, which hosted the indigenous Timucua people as well as settlements of this state's namesake \"Crackers.\" (*) </b>For ten points, name this Southern state known in the 2010s for a namesake \"man\" who commits unusual crimes in places like the Everglades.", "answer": "<b><u>Florida</u></b> (accept <b><u>Florida</u></b> Man)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Composer Aaron Copland [[KOHP-land]] set a speech at one of these events in</u></b> <b><u>Alton to music, and the recently invented Pitman Shorthand allowed writers to keep</u></b> <b><u>up with the orators at these events. The ability of territories to exclude (+)</u> slavery through local legislation was espoused during these debates in the Freeport Doctrine. A Democrat and a future (*) </b>Republican president vied for a Senate seat in Illinois during, for ten points, which 1858 debates?", "answer": "<b><u>Lincoln-Douglas</u></b> Debates (<b><u>Great</u></b> Debates of <b><u>1858</u></b> before \"1858\" is read; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Before assuming his most notable position, this man was told \"May God curse</u></b> <b><u>your studies\" during a recruitment attempt by future ally William Farel. This</u></b> <b><u>theologian helped build the case of heresy against Michael (+)</u> Cervetus, who was then burned at the stake. This reformer pleaded with Francis I to stop persecuting the Huguenots in his native country in the preface to his magnum opus, (*) </b><em>Institutes of the</em> <em>Christian Religion</em>. For ten points, name this French-Swiss reformer who expounded the doctrine of predestination while living in Geneva.", "answer": "John <b><u>Calvin</u></b> (or Jean <b><u>Calvin</u></b>; accept Jean <b><u>Cauvin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Following this event, Albert Henry Wiggin noted, \"We are reaping the natural</u></b> <b><u>fruit of the orgy of speculation in which millions of people have indulged.\" The causes</u></b> <b><u>of this event were investigated by the Pecora Commission, and it was partially blamed</u></b> <b><u>on (+)</u> Charles E. Mitchell. William C. Durant and members of the Rockefeller family tried to prevent this event, after which the Glass-Steagall Act was passed, mandating a separation between (*) </b>commercial and investment banks. For ten points, name this October 1929 event that brought in the Great Depression.", "answer": "1929 Wall Street <b><u>stock market crash</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Wall Street crash</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Great Crash</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}